<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category='std' ipr='trust200902'
     docName='draft-grozev-perc-ssrc-01'>

<?rfc toc='yes' ?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc iprnotified='no' ?>
<?rfc strict='yes' ?>
<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
  <front>

    <title abbrev='SSRC rewrite'>
        Allowing Synchronisation Source (SSRC) and Timestamp 
        Rewriting in Privacy Enhanced RTP Conferencing (PERC)
    </title>
    <author initials='B.' surname='Grozev'
            fullname='Boris Grozev'>
      <organization abbrev='Atlassian'>Atlassian</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>303 Colorado Street, #1600</street>
          <city>Austin</city>
          <code>78701</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-512-640-3000</phone>
        <email>bgrozev@atlassian.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
        <author initials='E.' surname='Ivov'
            fullname='Emil Ivov'>
      <organization abbrev='Atlassian'>Atlassian</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>303 Colorado Street, #1600</street>
          <city>Austin</city>
          <code>78701</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-512-640-3000</phone>
        <email>eivov@atlassian.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date />
    <abstract>
      <t>
        Privacy Enhanced RTP Conferenceing allows middle boxes (MDs) 
        to overwrite a certain set of fields in RTP packets, as long 
        as they preserve their original values in the Original Header 
        Block (OHB). This draft discusses the option of extending the 
        OHB so that it would also include the RTP timestamp and 
        Synchornization Source identifier (SSRC) within the set of 
        fields an SSRC can modify.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title='Introduction'>
      <t>
        In multi-endpoint RTP conferences, packet forwarding 
        middleboxes  (e.g. Selecting Forwarding Units (SFUs)) adapt to 
        variable  bandwidth conditions by selectively dropping a 
        subset of the  packets when forwarding traffic to some or all 
        recipients. These dropped packets may correspond to certain 
        participants, but more  importantly simulcast layers.
      </t>
      <t>
        A common model for implementing simulcast consists in having 
        senders send multiple resolutions to the middlebox, each with 
        its own SSRC, as well as distinct sequence number and 
        timestamp spaces. Middleboxes on the other hand, often choose 
        to  only make receivers aware of a single SSRC, 
        timestamp and sequence number space, as shown on the 
        figure below. 
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure title="Trickle State Updates" anchor="fig-arch">
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
 +------+                     +-----+                     +--------+
 |      |--SSRC1 Timestamp1-->|     |                     |        |
 |Sender|--SSRC2 Timestamp2-->| SFU |--SSRC4 Timestamp4-->|Receiver|
 |      |--SSRC3 Timestamp3-->|     |                     |        |
 +------+                     +-----+                     +--------+
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        The advantage of this model consists in the fact that 
        receivers require no custom logic to support it as all they 
        ever see  is a single incoming video stream. 
      </t>
      <t>
        In its current state the PERC double specification does not 
        allow for SSRC and timestamps to be overwritten, which makes 
        it impossible for SFUs to continue operating in this manner.
        This document therefore defines an extended OHB format and 
        explains the specifics of implementing SSRC and timestamp 
        rewriting within a PERC environment.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Extended Original Header Block (OHB) Format'>
      <t>
        The OHB header extension is defined in the ”double” draft 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-perc-double"/>. The current version 
        defines a structure which can contain atmost the original RTP 
        Payload Type (PT) and SEQ fields, and this restricts the MD to 
        only modifying thesetwo fields, while, as explained 
        before, for the simulcast usecase the MD may also need to 
        modify the SSRC and the timestamp.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification extends the OBH structure so that it can 
        contain the additional fields needed for the WebRTC 1.0 
        simulcast use case.  It still uses the 4-bit length field of 
        the header extension header <xref target="RFC5285"/> to encode 
        the structure of the remainingbytes.  Specifically, it encodes 
        which of these four fields will be present in the following 
        bytes:  Payload Type (PT, 1 byte, including an extra R-bit), 
        Sequence Number (SEQ, 2 bytes), SSRC(4 bytes), Timestamp (TS, 
        4 bytes).
      </t>
      <t>
        If the length field has a value of 0, 1 or 2 (indicating that
        there are respectively 1, 2 or 3 more bytes), then the format
        is exactly the same as in the current draft.  This means that
        an endpoint which implements the extended format can workwith 
        the current format without modification.
      </t>
      <t>
        The following table lists the fields which are  encoded (and 
        the order in which they are included) for the  different 
        values of the length field and the R-bit. The R-bit is the 
        most significant bit (MSB) of the PT field, and is present if 
        and only if the PT field is present. If the extension includes 
        the PT field, it consists of an R-bit (MSB) and 7 bits for the 
        original RTP Payload Type. The R-bit is used to encode which 
        fields are included, when there is ambiguity.
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure title="OHB Fields" anchor="fig-ohb">
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
      +---+-----------------+--------------+
      |len| R-bit set       |R-bit not set |
      +---+-----------------+--------------+
      | 0 |PT               |              |
      | 1 |SEQ              |              |
      | 2 |PT, SEQ          |              | 
      | 3 |SSRC             |              |
      | 4 |PT, SSRC         | PT, TS       |
      | 5 |SEQ, SSRC        |              |
      | 6 |PT, SEQ, SSRC    | PT, SEQ, TS  |
      | 7 |SSRC, TS         |              |
      | 8 |PT, SSRC, TS     |              |
      | 9 |SEQ, SSRC, TS    |              |
      | 10|PT, SEQ, SSRC, TS|              |
      +---+-----------------+--------------+ 
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        The fields encoded in the OHB header extension, for different 
        values of the length field and the R-bit.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Alternative format'>
        <t>
        In the context of SVC an MD might need to modify the M bit of RTP packets
        (for example when the higher layers of a frame are dropped, and the frame
        terminates "early").
        </t>
        <t>
        The original format from the "double" draft <xref target="I-D.ietf-perc-double"/>,
        as well as the format described above don't allow for the M bit to be modified.
        </t>
        <t>
        One more bit of information which may be desired to be transported from a PERC
        sender to an MD is whether a packet contains actual payload, or consists only of
        padding (i.e. discardable data). 
        </t>
        <t>
        These two bits can be transported with the following alternative format for the
        OHB header extension:
        <figure title="Alternative OHB format" anchor="fig-ohb-alt">
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |   ID  |  len  |P|S|s|T|M|p|0 0|
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>

        <t>
        Where:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t>
            P specifies the presence of a Payload Type byte.
          </t>
          <t>
            S specifies the presence of a Sequence Number field (2 bytes).
          </t>
          <t>
            s specifies the presence of a SSRC field (4 bytes).
          </t>
          <t>
            T specifies the presence of a Timestamp field (4 bytes).
          </t>
          <t>
            M contains the original value of the M bit.
          </t>
          <t>
            p is a padding-only bit, which indicates that the packet
            contains only padding and can be discarded.
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>

    </section>
    <section title='Security Considerations'>
      <t>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Acknowledgements'>
     <t>   
     </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title='Normative References'>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
    </references>
    <references title='Informative References'>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3550"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4588"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5285"?>
      <reference anchor='I-D.ietf-avtext-framemarking'>
        <front>
          <title>Frame Marking RTP Header Extension</title>
          <author initials='E' surname='Berger' fullname='Espen Berger'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials='S' surname='Nandakumar' fullname='Suhas Nandakumar'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials='M' surname='Zanaty' fullname='Mo Zanaty'>
             <organization />
          </author>
          <date month='March' day='13' year='2017' />
          <abstract>
            <t>
              This document describes a Frame Marking RTP header 
              extension used to convey information about video frames 
              that is critical for error recovery and packet 
              forwarding in RTP middleboxes or network nodes.
              It is most useful when media is encrypted, and essential 
              when the middlebox or node has no access to the media 
              decryption keys.  It is also useful for codec-agnostic 
              processing of encrypted or unencrypted media, while it 
              also supports extensions for codec-specific information.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-avtext-framemarking-04' />
        <format type='HTML'
                target='https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-avtext-framemarking-04' />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor='I-D.ietf-perc-double'>
        <front>
          <title>SRTP Double Encryption Procedures</title>
          <author initials='C' surname='Jennings' fullname='Cullen Jennings'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials='P' surname='Jones' fullname='Paul Jones'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials='A' surname='Roach' fullname='Adam Roach'>
             <organization />
          </author>
          <date month='March' day='13' year='2017' />
          <abstract>
            <t>
             In some conferencing scenarios, it is desirable for an 
             intermediary to be able to manipulate some RTP 
             parameters, while still providing strong end-to-end 
             security guarantees.  This document defines SRTP 
             procedures that use two separate but related 
             cryptographic contexts to provide "hop-by-hop" and 
             "end-to-end" security guarantees.  Both the end-to-end 
             and hop-by-hop cryptographic transforms can utilize an 
             authenticated encryption with associated data scheme or 
             take advantage of future SRTP transforms with different 
             properties.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-perc-double-03' />
        <format type='HTML'
                target='https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-perc-double-03' />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
